OK, let's get started.
You heard the bell and you know about Paolo's dogs and humans are reinforcement learning agents.
You remember that from yesterday.
So let's get started.
So we have an exciting lecture ahead of us because we're going to do some of what we couldn't do
yesterday.
We just start with transistors, and then we're going to build up to logic gates, and then we're
going to do a combination of logic.
In the meantime, we're going to introduce Boolean algebra, but probably many of you know what that
is.
Does that sound good?
All right, let's jump into it.
This is your extra credit assignment.
So for your reminder, deadline's March 21st, but no AI.
I'll remind you of that.
If we see AI, you'll get a 0.
I want you to learn.
That's why it's not like I don't want you to use AII think people should be using AI when whenever
it improves their productivity and makes them better at what they're doing.
But if the goal is to learn how something works, you don't start with AI, right?
Because unfortunately, it abstracts away some things.
And that's the whole purpose of this course.
Get rid of this magic that happens in how computers work, right?
Computers work because we built some things like transistors and we put them together in certain
ways so that we can do computation.
And all of the infrastructure, all of the higher level abstractions, AI, high level languages,
they're all built on top of it.
That's why I know AI over here.
And there are some reading assignments that I covered yesterday so you can take a look.
So this is the plan for today.
Let's see how much we can cover.
My hope is at least we'll cover some combinational logic circuits, maybe most of them.
Let's see.
Sounds good.
And we have an attentive set of people.
Because people who don't come on Fridays didn't come.
There's always a set of people who don't come on Fridays.
It's part of the weekend, I guess.
OK, so you've seen these slides.
All computers are built using the same building blocks.
But I see some people are online, so that's good.
I think we have a good following on YouTube.
Hopefully they're asking good questions and we don't have AI chat bots asking questions.
OK, Anyway, so we're going to cover the building blocks of modern computers, and we're going to
start with transistors because all modern computers are built with transistors.
And you can imagine modern computers built with mechanical components also.
We're not going to cover that.
You can imagine modern computers built with biological cells, which we don't know how to do at this
point, but that's a good area of investigation, and we're not going to cover that.
We're going to cover what we know how to build, which is transistors.
And semiconductor revolution has happened because people were able to fabricate these transistors
well, robustly, cheaply, efficiently.
And as a result, we can put trillions of these transistors on a wafer today.
And it's fascinating.
So we will see.
So what's the transistor?
Basically, these are what computers are built from.
So we're going to get get into that.
And these are relatively simple structures, simple to understand.
If you go into the lower level abstraction that we're not going to go into, there's a lot of
analogue operational properties of transistors, but we're going to draw a boundary of what we will
cover.
So just to give you an idea of what things were, the first microprocessor, Intel 404-4000, four in
1971 had 2300 transistors.
29 years later, Intel Pentium 4 had 42,000,000.
And more recently, 22 years later after that, Apple's M2 Max had 67 billion transistors.
These are mostly logic, actually.
You will see that these are chips that do computation, but then we also have chips that can store
data.
Here the transistor density is even larger.
Just to give you an example, the flash memory, one of the flash memories that was introduced in
2022, where dyes are stacked on top of each other, you had five trillion transistors on that chip,
which is fascinating.
This is larger than a wafer.
How much you can put on a wafer?
And these flash memories are really small actually.
So we're going to cover memory later on.
So in this lecture, we're going to look at how the MOS transistor works, metaloxide semiconductor as
a logic element.
And we're going to, this is the only lecture where we will touch the devices a little bit.
Actually, we may touch it a little bit in the timing and verification, but this is really going to
be the basics.
And then we're going to build logic on top of that.
So we're going to use these transistors to form logic gates and building.
On that, we're going to use these logic gates to build essentially A microprocessor over time.
Of course, combination logic first, sequential logic later.
Does that sound good?
So we're going to walk up essentially.
I mean, we could have started with the electron abstraction, but then this lecture will be much
longer.
It's better to draw the abstraction layer as a transistor.
And if you're really interested in how a transistor really works, you need to take a
microelectronics course offered by the Etet department, or you can find actually very good courses
online as well.
If you want recommendations, I'm happy to provide that.
OK, So what is this transistor thing?
Basically, people have figured out that by combining conductors, metals, insulators, oxide usually,
and semiconductors, you can come up with a transistor.
And this is a structure that can actually that looks kind of like this.
This is a real picture, an old one.
There's a gate through which you apply voltage and there's a source and drain that are essentially
wires.
You can think of them as well.
You can think of it that way.
And based on the voltage that you apply to the gate and based on the type of the transistor,
depending on how much voltage you apply, the source and drain get connected to each other or not
connected to each other.
So the wire, the transistor acts like a wire or an open circuit where the source and drain are not
connected.
That's the whole point of operation and that's what I'm going to go into in the next 10 slides or
so.
So why is this useful?
Essentially, we can combine these based on this operational principles.
We can combine different transistors and multiple of these transistors to realise simple logic
functions, For example, a knot function, inversion function, which we're going to start with.
And then we can do NANT or and NOR or XOR, And on top of that we can build addition.
On top of that we can build multiplication, etcetera.
And on top of that we can do matrix multiplication, which everybody's trying to optimise right now
with AI.
So essentially this is how things are built.
It's fascinating, right?
The simple thing, it was invented in 1950s.
OK, the electrical properties of metal oxide semiconductors, how do you fabricate them?
All of those are beyond the scope of this course.
They're actually courses by themselves in microelectronics.
If you take that course, you will go into electronic electrical properties of many, many, many
different types of transistors.
Fabrication is a totally different type of course.
How do you fabricate these?
How do you get these materials?
Then you go into the wet nut load, you go into a lab, and you actually potentially fabricate these
yourself.
So those are not our subject.
Our subject is assuming that these operate the way we're going to describe them to operate and build
a computer on top of that.
So there's a lot more at the lower level, basically, as you can see.
OK, yeah, that's where we draw the abstraction level.
But if you want to your textbook, Harris and Harris, which is actually a very nice textbook, I think
sections 1.6 and 1.7 go into a little bit lower abstraction levels.
If you're interested, I'm going to cover them a little bit because we need to touch some of these
things like power consumption, so stay tuned.
So there are two different types of MOS transistors, N type and P type.
N type looks like this.
We're going to go into a little bit more detail later.
And P type is usually denoted like this.
So there's some difference over here.
There's a little dot over here that's applied before the gate.
Dot means inversion usually.
So let's take a look at N type.
Both operate logically very similar to the way wall switches work.
So when I actually go to this wall switch, I'm scared of doing it.
What will happen?
IO, it says OK, it worked.
So the transistor is off right now, and the transistor is on right now.
I'm going to show you that.
So a wall switch can be constructed with a transistor actually.
So basically this is the N type transistor.
You have a gate and remember that we apply some voltage to the gate and if you apply high voltage,
let's say it's 3 volts, that's the maximum voltage for this type of circuit.
Then the circuit is closed or the transistor is turned on.
Let's say circuit is closed, meaning there this drain and source.
The transistor acts like a wire, it acts like a conductor basically.
It conducts whatever current there is between the drain and the source.
Make sense?
OK, now this is the P type.
For P type, for this transistor to get turned on, or for the circuit to be closed, the gate needs to
be supplied with voltage 0.
So it's exactly opposite of N type.
For the N type to turn on, you need to apply high voltage, 3 volts.
For the P type to turn on, you need to apply low voltage 0 volts.
Sounds good right?
Why does it work this way?
This way take a micro electronics design course.
But you can build things that work this way.
Yes, voltage may be relative to the source, but that's also below our level of abstraction.
Yes, for this to work correctly, your voltage needs to be above some level to turn on the
transistor.
That depends on how the circuit is designed, how large is the transistor, what kind of fabrication
technology you use.
A lot of things that are well beyond what we want to study.
Then this will become a microelectronics course.
But those are very good questions if you want to learn more microelectronics.
Makes sense.
OK, so how does a wall switch work?
As I showed you, there's a power supply and there's some lamp.
There's one lamp over here in this picture.
And if I go turn that off, the wall switch is not.
There's basically some line, some wire that's not connected that doesn't connect the power supply to
the lamp.
Basically the, the, the wires open and if I press the, in order for the lamp to glow, the electrons
must flow and they flow from the power supply to the lamp.
For that to happen, there needs to be a closed circuit from the power supply to the lamp and back to
the power supply.
And the lamp can be turned on and off by pressing that button over there, right, which is the wall
switch.
So I I press that button and the circuit is closed, right?
So basically instead of the wall switch, we could use an N type or P type transistor to make or
break the closed circuit.
So let's take the N type.
This is the schematic of an N type transistor.
If the gate of the N type transistor is supplied with high voltage, the circuit is closed.
Essentially the the connection from the source to drain acts like a piece of wire.
As I said earlier, depending on the technology, voltage can be.
So this kind of relates to your question.
Voltage can be high, 3 volts, 0.3 volts.
I'm going to assume 3 volts.
It doesn't matter.
That's not important.
You have a high voltage level and a low voltage level, right?
We're going to get to that when we talk about power consumption because voltage effects power a lot,
OK.
If the gate is supplied with 0 voltage, then the connection between the drain and source is broken,
so the circuit is open so you don't conduct anything.
OK, so transistors, a switch, this is the abstraction that we're going to work with.
So this is now I replace the wall switch with an N type transistor as you can see over here.
And when I apply 0 volts, the circuit is open so the light doesn't turn on.
When I apply high voltage, 3 volts to the gate, the circuit is closed, electrons flow and go back to
the power supply and the flow continues.
That's why the light turns on.
Makes sense, right?
OK, good.
This is the short time notation we're going to use.
It actually matters where you put things.
So this is the power supply, this is the lamp and this is the transistor, N type transistor over
here.
So we're going to get back to this.
We're going to form gates.
We're going to get rid of the lamp soon because lamp is something that we want to turn on, but we
want to do functions with it, right?
We want to multiply multiplication with lamps.
Possible, but maybe not so easy.
OK, so AP type transistor works in exactly opposite fashion from N type transistor.
Essentially this is N type and we already discussed this and P type is the opposite.
If you apply low voltage 0 volts to the gate, the circuit acts like a closed circuit.
The transistor turns on OK, and the circuit is yeah, I, I already said this basically.
And vice versa.
OK, makes sense.
It'll become more clear why we have two types.
Why not do everything with one type?
Because again, below the level of our abstraction, N type is good at pulling down the voltage, but
it's terrible at pulling up the voltage.
So if you want to construct a circuit with only N type transistors, you cannot do that.
You'll get a lot of noise and signal integrity issues.
Same with P type.
P type is very good at pulling up the voltage, but terrible at pulling down the voltage because of
the way they operate.
If you go underneath, again, take a microelectronics course, you will see that.
So you won't be able to construct a reliable circuit if you just use P type transistors.
That's why we have the CMOS or complementary metal oxide semiconductors, and I'm going to introduce
that.
So logic gates are one level higher in the abstraction.
Now that we know how a transistor works, we can go a little bit up.
How do we build logic gates?
OK, these logical units that's they're composed of individual transistors are called logic gates.
And they, they're going to implement simple Boolean functions.
That's where Boolean algebra comes in, because we're going to operate in the Boolean binary domain.
And George Bull has developed a mathematical logic that has been very useful in developing logic
circuits.
So let's take a look at how do we do these logic blocks.
Basically I said to this earlier, modern computers use both N type and P type transistors because
either of them alone is not good enough because of their analogue operational properties.
So we call this complementary medaloxide semiconductor technology CMOS, essentially all of the
technology that has been quite successful in the last decades.
So NMOS plus PMOS or CMOS.
So let's start with the simplest structure that exists in a CMOS technology looks like this.
You need basically an N type transistor at the bottom and AP type transistor over here, a power
supply 3 volts and a ground 0 volts.
And this is the input A connected to both the P type at the top and N type at the bottom.
And this is the output.
And yeah, I've already said that.
And a good question to ask is what does the circuit do Anybody.
Yes.
It's not gate.
Not gate.
OK.
Did you know it before or did you figure it out?
Figured it out.
OK, High voltage, SO3 volts.
Then the top one is open and the bottom one, it's closed, Yes.
So then the 0 volts is what gets outputted.
That's right.
If the input is 0 volts, then it's the other way.
Exactly.
Yes, exactly.
So logically, we can define as a not gate.
Your colleague explained it very nicely, but I'll explain it again for everyone.
So basically, let's take a look at what happens when the input is connected to 0 volts.
This guy is the input connector.
When this is 0 volts, this is what the circuit looks like.
Remember, open or closed.
If you're let's take a look at the P type transistor, the 0 volts, the P type transistor gets turned
on and the N type transistor gets turned off because the only way N type transistor will get turned
on is when it gets high voltage, right?
But it gets 0 volts.
This means that the power supply 3 volts gets connected to the output and 0 volts doesn't get
connected to the output.
That's a good thing.
And the output becomes 3 volts.
OK, so when you input 0 volts, you get 3 volts.
That's one input.
So P type transistor pulls up the output.
This is also, it's also good to remember P up and down.
You can easily confuse these things because if you don't know the fundamentals of how these operate,
that's how it is.
But it's good to remember there's a little bit of memorisation.
P type transistors are good at pulling up the voltage.
OK, what happens when the input is connected to three volts?
Exactly opposite thing.
Basically, the N type transistor gets turned on and ground gets connected to the output.
So output is pulled down to 0 volts and the P type transistor gets turned off.
As a result, you get 0 volts.
And N type transistors are good at pulling down the voltage.
That's why they're at the bottom.
They're connected to the ground.
P type transistors are connected to the power supply or power rail power line, and this is our NOT
gate.
It's a basic logical function.
It's an inverter.
In other words, it takes a complement of a.
Sounds good, right?
Beautiful.
Why do we call it not?
Because it takes an input 0 volts and the outputs 3 volts.
It takes an input 3 volts and outputs 0 volts.
It basically inverts and one possible interpretation of 0 volts and three volts in a digital circuit
is interpret 0 volts as a logical binary 0 value and interpret 3 volts as a logical 1 value.
Now we can actually have a truth table that looks like this.
Input over here, Output over here, input is A, output is.
YA truth table enumerates all possible input combinations and their corresponding output.
So I've already said this, but if a IS0P is, the P type transistor is turned on and N type is turned
off and output is 1.
Otherwise, if A is 1, you get the opposite effects and output becomes 0 and this is the
representation or boolean representation of the NOT gate.
Y = a bar complement.
Makes sense.
You've probably seen that representation.
So this is the logical representation.
This is a NOT gate.
Whenever you see logical representation of gates, inversion is signalled with this bubble.
If you don't have this bubble, then this triangle is a buffer, meaning Y is equal to A.
If you have this bubble after a triangle, then Y is equal to, not a complement of the A.
So a bubble always indicates inversion.
OK.
And truth table shows the logical output of the circuit for each possible input combination.
In this case, you have only one input, which is a, which means that there are only two possible
combinations in binary, zero or one, and the output is the opposite of that.
OK, that's our truth table.
Very simple truth table.
We're going to build more complex truth tables for other gates later on.
OK, so this sounds good.
We have the knot gate.
We can do only so much with not now.
Let's build some other things and we can do that based on the principles that we have seen.
So let's take a look at this one.
This is another gate.
You can see that the power line is over here, ground is over here, and I've connected 2 N type
transistors in series to the ground line and then to the output.
And then the input A goes to N1, input B goes to N 2.
And then I've connected 2P type transistors in parallel to the power line and they all are also
connected to the output line over here.
And input A goes to one, input B goes to 1.
And what does this do?
Yes, you have the answer.
It's what?
Not exactly.
Yes, I think it's a NAND.
OK.
So who votes for NAND?
OK, who votes for OR, who votes for and?
OK, then who votes for NOR just to be complete, OK, I think the NAND folks win, so let's go through
it.
So we're going to activate the inputs.
This is our truth table.
Because there are two inputs A&B, there are only four possible outputs, 2 to the two, right?
Because this is binary.
Again, each input can take 2 values, 00011011, and we're going to look at what happens to the output
Y.
So let's take a case of 00, basically, or or you can also actually think of it this way, right?
P1 and P2 are in parallel.
Only one must be on to pull up the output to three volts, right?
And one and N 2 are in series both and one and N2 should be on to pull down the output to 0 volts,
right?
But let's go through each case you the the result will be what I just said.
But so if A&B are both 0P1 and P2 are both on and one and N 2 are off, so output is 3 volts which is
1.
If a IS0B is 1P1 is ON, P2 is off and two is ON and one is off.
So this circuit is open, meaning that output is not connected to 0 volts, but output is connected to
three volts because 1 of this meaning P1 is on, so the output is 3 volts again.
If A is 1B is 0P2 becomes ON, P1 becomes off and one becomes ON and two becomes off.
The same situation happens and as a result output is still 3 volts 1.
The only different case is when N1 and N2 are both on, meaning A&B are one and one and N 2 are both
on.
So the output is connected to 0 volts and P1 and P2 are both off in this case because this is
complementary as you can see and output is not connected to three volts so output must be 0 right?
So this is it.
Basically this is a function.
In logical terms, Y is equal to 0 only if A&B are both one, right?
And this is an AND gate because it's the inverted and if A&B are AND means that output is 1 only if
A&B are one.
But what we want to get a zero only if A&B are one.
So that's the inverted version of and you get an inverter after an and.
Makes sense, right?
You can think about it if, but it's.
That's how the logic operates and this is how we denote it in our.
Basically dot indicates and A&B complement or or sometimes we omit dot AB.
If you put them together, that means A&B.
So complement of A&B which is and complemented which is NAND.
So Y is equal to NAND of A&B.
Makes sense, right?
OK, good.
This is basic logic.
Now we built NAND by adding one PMOS transistor in parallel to the PMOS transistor that we had in
the inverter and another NMOS transistor in series to the to the NMOS transistor we had in the
inverter.
So if you want to make a three input NT you add an N3IN series and AP3.
In parallel to the top right and three to the bottom.
So we can make actually three input 4 input 10 input million input things.
But now your latency may increase because you're going to, you're going to string a lot of things,
right?
We're going to talk about that also.
OK, sounds good.
So this is how NAND is denoted again, the bubble without the bubble, this Anand A&B, and with the
bubble this becomes Anand.
And this is the truth table that we just constructed.
And yeah, truth table on net.
OK, how do you build the end gate?
Before I go, actually I should say that if you want to do a NOR, you should put the P transistors.
If you want a 2 input NOR, put the P transistors in series over here and put the end transistors in
parallel at the bottom and you'll get a NOR.
OK, Yes.
What would happen if you were to connect the three volts to the 0 volts?
Yeah.
Meaning all of the circuits are turned on.
You don't want that because that's called a short circuit.
We're going to cover that.
You don't want a circuit where?
Yeah, Yeah.
We'll get to that.
Very good question.
OK, So how do you build the AND gate?
Now We have the NAND gate, which is this.
Sorry.
This is the AND gate.
This is the truth table for AND the truth table for NAND is exactly opposite of this, right And and
is this one.
So how do we get the AND gate?
And gate is actually inverted Nat, right?
So why don't we put a inverter to the output of Nat output of Nat.
So it looks like this and this is what I just did.
I just show you what I just said.
This is the NAND gate that we built.
This is the inverter that we first built.
And if you have NAND over here, this output over here is the NAND of A&B.
And if you invert it, you get the end of A&B.
Make sense, right.
OK.
So this is the NAND gate we have.
So we make an AND gate using one NAND gate and one NOT gate for a NAND gate, 6 transistors.
That's a lot, right?
OK, yes.
Could we also change where the P gates are to north and P&P?
You could, but it wouldn't work very well.
That's good.
That's the food for thought I had.
So you prefetched my question.
Can we not use fewer transistors?
That's what you're arguing for, right?
Basically, you put the N transistors connected to the three volts and the P transistors connected to
the 0 volts at the bottom.
You could do that.
There's nothing that prevents you from doing it.
The problem is what I just said earlier, N transistors.
N type transistors are very poor at conducting electrons.
They basically cannot pull up the voltage.
So what you would get at the end will not be 3 volts, it will be more like maybe 1 1/2 volts because
they don't conduct very well at the top.
And this is if you ask why this is the microelectronics part.
Their analogue operational properties are that way.
They're very good at conducting holes, but not electrons.
OK, OK, we're going to get to that.
But that's the reason why we have to go through this hassle of doing NAND 1st and then inverting it.
This is why CMOS logic is called inverting logic.
You basically have to deal with inverting all the time.
You don't get non inversion inverted version immediately.
You get an inverter very easily.
OK, but that's very good.
You're thinking, OK, so these are the gates that we have built essentially.
This is not inverter, this is the truth table.
This is the transistor level representation, this is NAND, this is the truth table transistor level
representation, and this is and truth table transistor level representation.
No magic as you can see.
And with this NAND gate alone, you can build any circuit.
That's the beauty of it.
Because NAND is logically complete, we're going to introduce that notion.
NAND is enough basically or you just have AND AND not, but it's the same thing, NAND, right?
Similarly, NOR is also logically complete, but we're going to get to logical completeness later on.
OK, So this is the general CMOS gate structure, essentially the general form used to construct any
inverting logic gate like what we have seen, not NAND.
NOR looks like this.
You have inputs and then you have a PMOS pull up network because PMOS is very good at pulling up.
That's connected to the power rail at the top three volts and bottom to the output, and it's also
connected to the NMOS pull down network at the bottom, which inputs are also connected to, and the
pull down network is connected.
To the ground at the bottom, that's the structure you want to build with CMOS technology.
You don't want the NMOS at the top for the reasons that I just said, but we're going to look at that
a little bit more.
So the networks may consist of transistors in series or in parallel.
You could be, you could have transistors in series at the top, or in parallel at the top, and in
series over at the bottom or in parallel at the bottom, depending on the function you want to
implement.
When transistors are in parallel, the network is on.
If one of the transistors is on, at least one of the transistors is on.
When the transistors are in series, the network is on if, all if and only if all of the transistors
are on.
OK, that's series and parallel nature of things.
And you've probably seen this in circuits at some point, right?
Correct.
Yeah.
OK, So PMOS transistors are used for pull up.
NMOS transistors are used for pull down and exactly 1 network should be on and the other network
should be off at any given time.
Your question was related to this.
If both networks are on at the same time, there is a short circuit meaning that the output is driven
to three volts and also 0 volts at the same time and you don't know what the result would be and
you don't want that.
If both networks are off at the at the same time, then inputs are not connected to the output, so
output is undefined.
Whatever value was there before is not driven out.
So this is actually represented with AZ, as we will see in Boolean logic.
This is not necessarily bad if you know what you're doing.
The first one's bad because you cannot have 3 volts and 0 volts at the same time.
There are some conflicting thing that happens in the circuit.
Then you may actually burn the circuit potentially, depending on how things work.
The second one, if you know what you're doing, sometimes it's going to be useful, as we will see
later on.
OK, so why do we have the structure?
Addressing the question earlier, most transistors are imperfect switches.
They're not perfect switches.
So the abstraction that I had works only so much.
If you try to be smart about where to put things, then you need to know what's going on underneath.
So basically, if you really want to change how things work, at some point you need to know the
abstract.
You need to go down the abstraction level.
So essentially, PMOS transistors pass ones well, but zeros poorly.
Poles carry charge by the electrons don't move.
Their mobility is low because of the way they're constructed.
NMOS transistors are exactly opposite.
Electrons carry charge, they can move fast, but holes don't have enough mobility.
As a result, PMOS transistors are up, so they're at the power rail and NMOS transistors are down.
They're good at pulling down the output.
This is why we have an N that's built with NAND and NAND plus not as opposed to only four
transistors.
And if you want to learn more about this section 1.7 and H&H Harris, and Harris is very good in this
description.
This is a summary of it.
OK, so let's talk about latency and then we'll talk a little bit about power.
So which one's slower transition series or transition in parallel?
Anybody who says series, I hear series.
OK, who says in parallel?
OK, the series folks win.
And they're correct because series connections are slower than parallel connections because there
are multiple transistors that need to be turned on so that the entire series of transistors acts as
a single wire, right?
And if all of them need to be turned on, there's a lot more resistance on the wire.
And resistance is really what determines how long your latency is to move the voltage from one
location to or to move the electrons or holes from one location to another.
Whereas in parallel, what happens is if only if one transistor is on the source is connected, drain
and as a result you don't care what happens with the other transistors, right?
There's only that transistors resistance.
So how do you alleviate this latency?
Reduce the series connections as much as possible.
Again, there's some example from H&H which is not used in modern processors, so I'm not going to go
into that.
But people have experimented with using only NMOS type of logic.
It's called pseudo NMOS logic so that you can have only parallel connections.
But this is very difficult to do in general.
But people do play a lot of tricks to try to reduce the series connections as much as possible.
So you may want to actually have gates that have fewer transistors in series and you may want to
have gates build build other gates on top of that as much as possible.
OK, power consumption, this is very important to describe.
Not enough goes into it.
We're going to talk a lot more about power later.
So there are two types of power consumption that happens in circuits.
1 is the power that's used to charge the capacitance.
As signals change, signal changes from zero to 1, one to zero.
So whenever you're switching, you consume power.
If input is 0 and output becomes one, inverter consumes power.
If input is 1, output becomes zero.
They you consume power basically.
This is really a functional multiple things.
One is voltage in the middle over here 1 is capacitance of the circuit, which I will not get into.
But this depends on how much load you have on the circuit, how many the characteristics of the
transistors and how many transistors you have that's hanging off your circuit.
And F is the frequency of change.
How frequently do you change?
How fast do you change from zero to 1 and 1 to 0?
OK.
So I think I kind of said that or charging frequency of the capacitor.
So you can see that if you want to reduce the dynamic power consumption, you may want to reduce the
frequency.
We're going to talk about frequency later on.
You may want to reduce the voltage because there's a cubic relationship, there's a quadratic
relationship between power and voltage.
The higher the voltage, the much higher the power, and This is why exactly people are trying to
reduce the voltage as much as possible in existing microprocessors.
3 volts is actually too high.
You want to have 0.1 volts.
The problem is, as you go into lower voltages, it becomes harder to turn on the transistor, right.
There was a question related to this early on.
The transistor may not operate correctly, but lower voltage is good for power, lower voltage is not
good for latency.
So there's a fundamental tension between power consumption and performance, on the other hand, and
reliability on the other hand.
You may consume higher power and you get higher performance and higher reliability.
If you want to reduce power, you may get lower performance and lower reliability.
OK, this is very fundamental.
You will see this in many, many, many other ideas also.
Higher power, higher performance.
OK, what else do I want to say over here?
So more complex circuits increase C, the capacitance.
So that's also important to think about.
So lower complexity is good for power.
Also, another thing to think about is the frequency.
The charging frequency of the capacitor is dependent on voltage as well.
So that's you can there.
There's an equation which I'm not going to go into, but frequency is a function of voltage.
Frequency can become higher with voltage.
So if you replace F with a function of V, you will see that there is a cubic relationship between
power and voltage rate.
So voltage actually kills you in a sense in terms of power consumption.
Makes sense.
Ideally you want to reduce voltage, but we've seen the downsides also.
It's all trade off in the end.
There's also static power consumption, which is the power that's used when you don't change
anything.
The circuit is sitting there, you're not applying any input, or you've already applied your inputs
and nothing is changing in the circuit anymore.
But the circuit still consumes power because it's connected to some power source.
And this happens because there's leakage in the power supply.
So this power rail, and then there's a transistor connected to it.
There's some leakage current that keeps.
Flowing in the circuit, and this is very hard to minimise.
And with smaller technologies it becomes a bigger chunk of the power.
And this is essentially the equation.
This is the equation for the static power consumption.
It's voltage times the leakage current.
So right now, for example, my circuit may not be doing anything in my pocket, but it it's consuming
leakage power.
So how do you actually alleviate the sort of thing people do?
Power gating, meaning if a circuit is not used, you stop powering it.
OK, this is, you can think of it as I'm not using my computer, I'll unplug it completely, right?
You can do this at smaller parts of a chip.
If an adder is not being used, for example, you can power gate the adder.
If a multiplier is not used, you can power gate it.
OK, but this is important also.
So it's supply voltage, time leakage current, energy consumption, which we care about is essentially
power times time, or the integral of how much power you're consuming over time, right?
Maybe I can use this over here if you help me, because I don't know how to use these things.
This is why we need robots, as you can see.
Maybe I'll be replaced with a robot 10 years down the road.
Would you guys like that?
I don't know.
I think robots have a great role to play in education.
We haven't.
So basically power and energy are related, but different concepts.
You've probably seen it in physics.
OK, you can see it.
OK, zoom out.
OK, maybe I'll use this light because how do you zoom out even more?
OK, sounds good.
OK, so maybe this is so this is time your circuit is running and this is power, and your power may
change.
So there's some static power if you if you don't turn off the circuit, there's some static power
that you consume for a given circuit.
And then there's some dynamic power on top of that that you add.
And this power may change depending on the activity that happens in the circuit.
It may shoot up significantly.
It may shoot down OK, and maybe at some point you turn off everything, right?
And then you get to 0.
So energy is really the curve, the integral of this power curve over time, right?
That's the energy you consume and that's what determines your battery life.
Makes sense, right?
Energy determines your battery life and also essentially your how much your power bill as well.
But there's another thing that's important, which is the total power consumption.
So there is some amount of power you can supply to the circuit that the circuit can tolerate.
And if you if you, if the circuit requires much more power to do all of the computation, it may
actually not work well.
So this is called the total design power or maximum power.
So you don't want to get into a situation where the maximum power you can supply to the circuit is
smaller than the power draw of the circuit because so, so many activity is going on in the circuit
that you cannot supply enough power.
So when you design A processor today, we design processors and this maximum power is a big
constraint.
We have so many transistors that we can put on in a circuit and we have, if you actually power all
of them on at the same time, if all of them are switching at the same time, you will need a whole
lot more power to power up everything.
So when you look at the processor today, because we have billions of transistors, you don't power up
everything at the same time.
So a part of the processor is actually, most of the processor is actually kind of silent.
It's not doing anything.
And if you run into a situation like this, this is called essentially it could, it could be some
sort of power emergency.
Usually the processor takes some action or you don't need to or, or it has some mechanism so that
you don't actually exceed the total power.
OK.
So this is important to distinguish, this is the distinction between maximum power consumption or,
or it's also called total design power, sometimes TDP versus energy.
Energy is really what determines your battery life.
Maximum power or total design power is what really determines how much activity you can have in a
given chip.
And these are two very different things, but they're both related to power consumption in the end.
Makes sense.
OK.
So maybe we can go back to I don't want to touch it because there's an expert who can touch it.
On power, yes, yes, I mean it depends because people have come up with a lot of solutions but the
leakage also like power gating, but it could easily be 40% if you don't have any solution to the
problem because what happens is especially when the circuit becomes smaller, the technology scaling
then it's called Denard scaling.
It's ended for some time, but as the circuit becomes smaller, you can reduce the supply voltage, but
the leakage current actually becomes constant.
So a relatively or increases potentially.
A relatively the dynamic power consumption reduces, but the leakage power consumption, it becomes a
bigger fraction.
But these are changing.
These are it's become very difficult to scale the circuits going into the future.
So scaling the voltage has become difficult also.
OK, OK, so let's talk about more logic gates.
This was important.
I think power is something everybody needs to care about because it has a lot of implications on
cooling power up and also sustainability.
In the end, a lot of the sustainability issues are because of the hardware cost as well as the power
consumption of circuits.
OK, these are some of the common logic gates.
We've seen a lot of them.
Buffer is essentially non inverting inverter.
I like thinking of it that way.
It's kind of a oxymoron, but it's essentially A buffer.
It amplifies a signal, but it doesn't have a logical effect on the signal.
We've seen all of these XOR.
Have you seen XOR?
Point probably have seen OK, XOR is basically this function over here and there's XNOR over here.
So let's talk about larger gates.
I already said this.
This is the three input AND gates as you can see, sorry, three input NAND gate.
See I've three input NAND gate, but you can actually have a lot of these.
Let me cover Moore's Law and then we'll take a break.
This is very quick.
Moore's Law has enabled a lot of essentially the ability to reduce the size of these basic
transistors, has enabled us to put a lot of transistors on a chip.
And this enabled a lot of the techniques that are that are going to come up in the rest of this
course.
So this is what Moore originally plotted in 1965.
You can see that he looked at how many components you can put on an integrated circuit and he
figured out that it's increasing exponentially.
OK.
And there's another picture over here.
This actually the real economic aspect of Moore's Law, which is a number of components per
integrated circuits increasing.
And this is a relative manufacturing cost per component.
And over years, both both the number of components is increasing exponentially and the cost of
manufacturing is also reducing.
And as a result, the sweet spot of how many components you put on an integrated circuit is reducing
exponentially again.
And that's him and that's the graph.
So you can see a lot of graphs like this, which is good.
This is my recommended reading.
There are a lot of interesting things in this three page paper that he wrote in 1965 here.
Basically by 1975, economics may dictate squeezing as many as 65,000 components on a single silicon
chip.
It's kind of funny.
In 2022, it was 67 billion.
And another quote over here, will it be possible to remove the heat generated by 10s of thousands of
components in a single silicon chip?
So that's also related to power.
Power leads to heat, temperature increases and you need to cool down things, right?
So that's why you should not, you should reduce power and not operate at very high temperatures.
So how do you enable these smaller transistors?
Manufacturing lower level is important.
So there's a lot of innovation that has happened in manufacturing and semiconductor manufacturing is
actually one of the big political issues in the world today, unfortunately.
But that's how it is.
And it's going to become more and more difficult, probably using materials.
Materials has also been important.
Manufacturing is essential fabrication technologies.
How do you actually come up with a fabrication technology that can etch smaller and smaller and
smaller structures on a piece of silicon, right?
Using materials is better properties.
People have actually invented a lot in materials.
That's going to be even more important into the future, more manufacturing, precision manufacturing
machines for doing this.
People use light to actually pattern things.
And also a new device technologies like different types of transistors.
We covered some type of transistor.
These are all CMOS transistors in the end, but they they differ in how they put the gate, how they
fabricate the gate and how they fabricate the drain and source, etcetera.
Our picture was quiet old.
There are many different types of things, so if you're interested in these things, there are nice
videos on this.
This is one of them.
And you can see that this is the scale of the transistor today somewhere over here compared to
1970s.
OK.
This is one of the manufacturing technologies that's used today.
I'm not going to talk about this, but this is for your benefit if you're interested.
This is definitely below our lower level of abstraction, but my point is there's a lot of innovation
at the bottom, meaning lower levels like devices that we're not going to cover in this course.
And that is enabled what we're going to build on top.
Never forget that.
It's really important because sometimes people say, oh, there's nothing happening at the bottom, but
there's a lot happening at the bottom.
And that's why we have these very powerful devices today.
So this goes back to Feynman.
OK, this is a paper review for you.
This is an optional assignment, no extra credit.
Last year it was Extracred because we asked people to not use AI, but then a lot of people used AI
and we had to go through a lot of boring reviews.
We're going to find another solution to the Extracred assignments this year, but this is for your
benefit.
Reading that paper would enhance you.
This is a good place to take a break.
We'll start combination logic circuits today.
Let's take an 11 minute break because we're running late.
So when the bell rings, the food is here.
The food for the brain, not food for the digestive system.
Somehow the bell is it's not working.
I don't know what happened.
How about now?
All good.
OK, somehow the bell is not hearable by me or it's not working, but it's a flaky bell, like a flaky
circuit.
OK, so now we're going to talk about combinational logic circuits.
Actually, we have built some combinational logic circuits.
As you can see, we understand the workings of the basic logic gates.
What do we do next?
We are going to build some of the structures that are important components of the micro architecture
of a computer.
So what's a logic circuit?
The logic circuit is composed of some inputs, as you've seen, some outputs and some specification of
it.
There's a functional specification which we are concerned with in this lecture, and there's also a
timing specification, how long things take.
We're not going to talk about that for now.
There is a separate lecture we're where we're going to deal with timing, but functional
specification describes the relationship between inputs and outputs.
What does, how does the circuit take the inputs and transform them to the outputs?
What's the value of the outputs as a function of the inputs?
Timing specification describes a delay between inputs changing and the outputs responding.
So for now, ignore the timing.
We're going to look at only the functional specification.
So there are multiple different types of circuits.
We're going to start with combinational logic circuits.
These are memory lists.
As I mentioned yesterday, outputs are strictly dependent on the combination of input values that are
being applied to the circuit right now, OK?
They're not a function of what happened in the past.
Later we will learn sequential logic that has memory that can store what has happened in the past,
meaning history and outputs in a sequential circuit will be determined based on the current inputs
as well as historical or stored data.
Makes sense, right?
So sequential circuit is of course more powerful because it has a combination logic inside it as
well as storage elements.
So we're going to build storage elements next week.
For now, we're not going to store no memory.
So let's start with Boolean logic equations.
Functional specification is essentially it specifies the outputs in terms of inputs.
What is a function?
So a function.
You've seen mathematical definitions of function in the past.
Probably it's a unique mapping of input values to output values.
The same input values always produce the same output value every time, and there is no memory in
this function.
Output does not depend on past input values.
So this is a full one bit adder.
Basically you have AB2 bits of a value, a single bit, and then carry in.
There's a carry that happens in addition, as you know, and then there's a sum bit and then there's a
carry out.
And this is the functional specification of a one bit adder.
Some is really the XOR of ABC and carry out is a three input majority function that is specified
like this A&B or A&C in or B&C in.
If at least two of these ABCS are true, you get the true you get, you get one at the end.
Otherwise, you get a zero and three input.
XOR is if you have an even number of OK, I'm not going to go through that.
You can think about that because we're going to construct that later on.
So we've seen simple equations.
This is, again, just to jog your memory, this is an inverter A, a bar, essentially this is A and B.
This is just to set terminology.
This is really an AND gate A&B.
It's kind of like a multiplication symbol, but it's really.
And and this is A or B.
OK, so Boolean algebra is really based on is an algebra of of ones and zeros.
To manipulate these equations with and or not an operations, you start with some axioms and we'll
see some axioms.
These are basic things about objects and operations.
You just assume to be true at the start and you derive laws and theorems, which we're going to look
into.
Also, they allow you to manipulate Boolean expressions and equations.
They also, importantly for the purposes of digital design, allow us to simplify boolean expressions.
You may have a function with lots of inputs and a huge specification, but if you use some of these
laws and theorems and axioms, you can actually reduce it to a much smaller specification, meaning
you can actually design A much smaller circuit to implement that function, which may not be
expressed in its minimal form.
Makes sense.
OK, So we'll see example of this.
So you can derive more sophisticated properties for manipulating digital designs essentially.
So we'll see applications of it.
How many of you have seen Boolean algebra before?
Now that I've introduced a little bit more, probably all of you, right, In high school, Yes, in an
earlier course here.
Which course?
Who wants to discrete math?
Yes, exactly.
Maybe the notation may be a bit different and you that you see in discrete math or is it exactly the
same?
OK, it's a bit different, yeah, unfortunately, but that's how it is.
You just need to get used to the notation over here.
This is how things are done in the circuit community or digital design community.
So these are some axioms.
So I'm not going to go through these in detail.
Probably, you know, a lot of these, this is just jogging your memory.
Let's say commutative laws A or B is the same as B or A.
You can swap inputs.
Basically.
A&B is the same as B&A, identity elements, A or Z, or is A, A and 1 is A.
There's distributive laws.
A or B&C is A or B&A or C and the other way around.
So the the the and and OR operations distribute over each other and complement A or A bar is 1A and
a bar is 0.
Sounds good, right?
There's a duality property in Boolean algebra.
All of the axioms come in dual form.
Anything true for an expression is also true for its dual.
So this is actually useful when actually you manipulate circuits, different gates, let's say.
So any derivation you make that is true can be flipped into a dual form and it stays true.
So more formally, you form a dual of a boolean expression by replacing every AND operation with an
OR operation, every OR operation with an AND operation, every constant one with a constant 0, every
constant zero with a constant one.
But you don't change any of the literals or play with the complements.
So for example, A and.
So if if this is your equation, this is correct.
It's it's it basically show the distributed law if you change every and every dot to plus over here
in the top and every cluster dots, there are no constants here.
It's essentially the same equation, right?
Basically it's it's the dual equation.
It's not the same equation, but it's the dual.
If this is true, then this is also true, OK.
And this is the distributed law of the other way around, as you can see.
OK, So there are also some other use for loss.
And these are the duals of it.
You can see that for your for yourself here.
For example, X or zero is X logically.
And dual means change the OR to and and change the zero to 1X.
And one is X Sounds good.
I'll buy that.
OK.
And you can do the other one for yourself.
X or X is xnxx is also the X.
That's good.
There's no dual for this because it's the same and complementary as a dual also.
And then there's commutativity.
OK, let's take a look at some more associated laws.
We've seen this is an example over here, distributed law we've seen, we haven't seen associated, but
it's kind of obvious.
Basically parentheses order doesn't matter.
Simplification theorems are useful for simplifying logic and actually what people, what electronic
people have automated a lot of these design essentially today there are a lot of electric
electronic design automation tools that can compute this Boolean algebra and give you a nice
circuit.
With AI you can do even better today actually.
So these are some simplification theorems as you can see, X&Y plus or X&Y bars X and the dual is
also true.
I'll let you study the duals on your own, but I will say that some of these actually happen in
circuits a lot.
X or X&Y is X and you can prove that clearly.
We're going to prove that in a later slide soon.
So if you have something like this X or X&Y, implementing an AND gate and an OR gate is a waste
because you could just have X right, and a wire.
That's it.
Because this, this simplifies the X essentially.
OK, so let's take a look at proving things relatively quickly.
Let's let's assume that this is our theorem.
X&Y or X&Y bar is equal to X.
How do we prove it?
We basically take out X on the left and based on the distributed laws, X&Y or Y bar is equal to X&Y
or Y bar is essentially 1 and then X and one is X.
So we've proven it and you can prove the next one also similarly this way.
And This is why this circuit is not good to implement.
You just have a wire, makes sense, right?
So if you have this at some point in your circuit, don't implement an AND gate and an OR gate, just
have a wire to X.
Makes sense, right?
This is basic logic again.
But hopefully you see the connection to how you implement gates, because logic is gates, and the
more gates, the more complicated your Boolean equation, the more gates usually.
And some gates may be more expensive than others.
So you may actually want to do the simplification to avoid some gates that are more expensive than
others.
And that's essentially what circuits minimisation tools do today.
So let's take a look at a few more laws.
How many of you have seen the Morgan's laws?
OK, good.
I'll go through this even more quickly then.
So this is a transformation.
I like thinking of it as this way.
It's a logical thing if at least one of ABC is true.
It is not the case that ABC are all false.
That's the best way I can think of the the Morgan's Law and the other way around is true.
So this is what this law says.
And then there is also an AND version of it as opposed to or version over here.
OK, now what is the Morgan's Law useful for?
Probably you didn't go into this in discrete math.
Essentially, you can change the type of gates that you want to implement the same function for.
For example, let's assume that this is you have nor basically, nor is equivalent to end with inputs
complemented.
So this is our nor gate X nor YA is equal to X nor Y.
And if you apply the Morgan's Law on it, you'll get X complement and Y complement.
Makes sense, right?
It's it's the same thing basically.
Now the difference is the type of gate that you have, right?
This the NOR gate.
This the NAND gate.
If for some reason your NOR gate is faster than your NAND gate, you may want to choose the NOR gate.
If for some reason your NAND gate is faster or lower power than your NOR gates, you may want to
choose the NAND gate.
These are essentially implementing the same logic function, but the underlying gates maybe may have
different speed, different power consumption, different reliability, depending on how things
operate.
OK, we're not going to go into that in detail, but that's what this these laws are useful for
partially.
Similarly, NAND is equivalent to OR with inputs complemented, as you can see over here.
OK, so we're going to use Boolean equations to represent logic circuits.
The functional specification.
We cannot do that with timing.
We will methodically transform the function into simpler functions which will lead to different
hardware realisations, hopefully smaller and smaller.
This is called logic minimisation or logic simplification essentially, and we can automate this
process if you feed all of these rules to a program.
These are called computer aided design or electronic design automation programs.
They can do all of this for you.
And again, as I said today, there's AI assisted EDA programs that are actually quite good, but you
need to know the basics of how they operate.
OK, so different Boolean expressions lead to different logic gate implementations or realisations as
we have seen, which may have implications on hardware area, cost, latency and energy.
But usually, how do you start?
So a function may be represented with an infinite number of Boolean equations.
You can actually come up with this kind of useless exercise maybe of representing a function with an
infinite number of Boolean equations, right?
You keep adding useless terms, but normally what's you need if you want to actually automate this
process, you want to start with something that's universally agreed upon and that's why people have
developed these canonical forms or standardised representations.
In other words, it's a they they enable a single universally agreed on way of representing A boolean
function starting from its truth table.
And there are two forms.
I'm going to cover the sum of products form in a bit more detail than product of sums form.
The key idea is very simple.
Essentially assume you have a truth table.
This is all words, but I'm going to give you an example of boolean function F You express this
function in terms of the inputs in a standard manner.
Sum of products form express the truth table as a true level boolean expression.
That's the idea.
Every truth table can be expressed as A2 level boolean expression for a given input.
A given output, sorry, it contains all of the input variable combinations that result in A1 output.
So you look at the output there, which ones are one and you identify them.
And if any of the combinations of input variables that results in a one is true, then the output is
one.
Right?
That's basic logic.
Again, this is how I can I can express that output.
If any of the input combinations that results in a one for the output is true, then the function is
true.
The output evaluates to true.
So essentially you can express the function as the OR of all input variable combinations that result
in a 1.
So let's take a look at this with an example.
It's much easier with an example.
There are also some terminology like this called disjunctive normal form min term expansion.
We'll see why it's called a min term.
Basically this is a truth table of a three input function ABC 3 inputs there 8 possible minterms
meaning 8 possible rows.
OK you list all of them and you look at the value of output bits function F and you figure out which
ones are one.
So for find all the input combinations, an input combination is called a minterm for which the
output of the function is true and there are five of them as you can see.
And basically you express this function as an OR of all of those input combinations.
So these are values that are assigned to ABC.
If a IS0B is 1 and C If A is 0 and B is 1 and C is 1, the output is 1.
Or if A is 1 and B is 0 and C is 0, the output is 1 and you get the rest of it, right?
So basically this is how you express the function in a canonical form.
Function is of or of all min terms input variable combinations that result in a 1.
So function is a bar BCF is true, F eval is to one if a bar BC values to one or AB bar C bar eval is
to one or AB bar C values to 1...
makes sense right?
It's basic logic again.
And this is the sum of products form.
And all boolean equations can be written in sum of products form.
And this sum of product form forms a unique signature for this three input function where the bottom
5 rows evaluate to one, right?
Hopefully that makes sense.
OK, so let's go through this relatively quickly.
Complement, you know what a complement is variable with a bar over it.
Literal is variable or it's complement.
Implicant is product and of literals.
So we're going to use and of literals in sum of products form.
Mean term is the product that includes all input variables.
Basically, if you have a three input function, all of the input variables should be there because we
want a canonical or standardised form that everybody agrees on, right?
If someone omits one input, somebody else can omit another input.
So that's not a standardised form.
We want something standardised.
Next term is going to be important for product of sums form.
This is the sum that or that includes all of the input variables.
So truth table is the signature of a boolean function, but it's an expensive representation.
Many boolean functions can have the same truth table as we discussed, and we want to have a
standardised form and minimise that later on.
I've discussed all of them earlier, so we've already done this sum of products form.
This is actually a copy of the previous slide, but let's take a look at why this works.
So the function evaluates are true if any of the products or midterms causes the output to be one,
right?
So let's take a look at one example.
If a IS1BB is 0 and C is 1, you evaluate one, right?
So this input activates that term and only the shaded term will be one.
No other product terms will turn on, they will all be 0.
So if inputs ABC correspond to a product term in the expression, you get one for output.
If the inputs ABC do not correspond to any product term, hopefully this part over here, then you get
0 as the output.
OK, these are actually very simple things, so that's why I'm going through this relatively quickly.
So how do we standardise this?
Essentially, if we agree on the order of variables in the rows of the truth table, we can enumerate
each row with a decimal number that corresponds to the binary number created by the input pattern.
Basically you're you're you're enumerating all of the min terms for an N input function, and an
input function has two to the end minterms, right?
So in this case, we have a three input function.
You have 8 minterms.
So this particular minterm is 100.
We ordered them 000001010.
Basically it's increasing.
And the decimal version of this is 4.
So this is minterm 4 as you can see.
And this is midterm 7 decimal seven M7, OK.
And the function can be expressed as a sum of products, sum of midterm 34567, or you can use a
summation notation, right?
So if someone gives you this thing for a three input function, you know exactly what that function
is and everybody agrees on that function, right?
OK, so and you know exactly what the min terms are, right?
Then this is a short term notation.
So I think I've gone through this relatively quickly.
If you know that function, you can write out them in terms and then you know that this is a very
expensive form.
Potentially it may be the minimal form, you don't know that yet.
And then you can go and minimise it.
I will not go through this, but you can do it yourself.
It turns out the minimal form is a plus BC, but that's not a canonical form.
If you gave a plus BC, nobody would know that this would be a how many input function, right?
You don't know basically makes sense, right?
OK, so this is the realisation of this.
This is the standard form sum of products form of this function and this is the minimised version of
this function.
Those are two different things.
You could of course implement this function with like this, right?
Except it'll be very expensive, a lot of gates right now.
We will see actually how that is implemented soon.
OK, so this is how it's implemented.
Sum of products leads to two level logic.
This is how you have 3 min terms over here, A bar B, bar CAB A/B, bar C, bar AB, bar C, and then the
OR.
So you can see that sum of products is actually very regular.
You can actually form all of the min terms and then decide which ones to pick at the input of the OR
gate, right?
OK, clearly this is not minimal, so you can make it minimal.
OK, this is a summary.
I'm not going to go through this, but hopefully you got the idea of sum of products.
Products of sums is essentially the opposite, meaning instead of looking at the bits output where
the output is true, meaning 1, you look at where the output is 0.
Or another way, it's the De Morgan of sum of products of F bar you find all the input combinations
Max terms for which the output of the function is false.
And then and the function is expressed as the end of all input variable combinations that result in
a 0.
So this is the same function, exactly the same as what I showed you.
We look to the 0 outputs and we express things like this.
So product of sums, the function is false if this input combination is false or this input
combination is false or this input combination is false, right?
Or another way actually I should say that I should say it more correctly.
The function is false if you get this input combination or if you get this input combination or if
you get this input combination.
OK, so each sum term represents one of the zeros of the function.
I already said this if any of the sums cause the output to be 0.
And you can actually see that, right?
For example, if ABC are all zeros, this term will be 0 and the function will evaluate to 0.
If ABC are like this 001, this will evaluate to 0.
If ABC are 010, this will evaluate to 0.
If ABC is 111, all of these will evaluate to 1.
As a result, you'll get the output to be one, right?
That's the idea.
That's what you should get.
OK, so I'll go through this relatively quickly also because we kind of covered it with sum of
products.
This is actually the Morgan of SOP of F bar.
This is what I said earlier.
If you have one input the if, if it matches the Max term that is part of the product of sums, then
you get an output 0, which is what you should get.
OK only one of the products will be 0.
Anything added with 00.
That's why it works.
Basically.
Again, it's logic, basic boolean logic.
OK how do you write it?
Essentially I'll go through this again.
So basically this is the Max term notation.
So we had the minterms, remember now we have the Max terms.
Essentially this function can be expressed as a product of some of the Max terms that lead to an
output of 0.
Remember the first 3 Max terms?
Led to an output of 0.
The same function can be expressed as a product of Max term 012, and this is the Max term.
When someone gives you a large M Max term zero, that means a + b + C over here.
So you can easily map it, right?
That's how we represent the function.
So you will find the Max term.
You will form the Max term around the zeros of the function.
Note that this is not the complement of the function.
This is exactly the same function, right?
What I showed you is the same function for which we wrote the sum of products form.
Meaning products of Max term 01/2 equals sum of min terms 34567, right?
That's essentially the same function.
OK, these are useful conversions.
That's essentially what I said.
Min term to Max term conversion.
These two are the same functions.
You basically if if a function is represented in terms of there it's Max terms, product of Max
terms, you can represent defs some of the min terms that's are not overlapping with the Max terms,
OK, And vice versa.
That's the vice versa part.
How do you get the complement of the function?
Let's assume that this is our function and this is the complement of it.
This is a sum of min terms.
Complement means you complement the function.
Zeros become the zeros in the output becomes one once the ones in the output become zeros.
That means that exactly the complement of the min terms should lead to ones.
So instead of writing min terms 34567, make your function 1 min term 012 make the function one,
right?
OK, so I'm going through this relatively quickly again because it's the same with product of sums
and you can also do the min term expansion to Max term expansion.
I'll let you I'll let you think about that.
OK, so we've gone through a lot of this Boolean algebra.
It's relatively simple.
Essentially in the end, it's Boolean logic and we can simplify SOP or POS form of any function in a
methodical way.
You start with this canonical form and you can automate all of this.
You start with truth table actually initially and then that's you can construct an SOP or POS form
and you use Boolean simplification rules to reduce the circuit.
So I can reduce a full one bit adder to what we see over here and we will see that later.
So we've already seen actually this is the sum of products form of function, YA particular function.
You can reduce it to this.
And again, I'll let you do that reduction.
You'll do a lot of that reduction in your exercises and maybe in some of the exams also.
Usually there are questions that come up from this in the exam.
I think there are easy questions in general.
OK, if there are no questions, let's jump into some combinational blocks.
This is actually needed so that we can actually understand how we represent all of the combinational
blocks that are going to come.
OK, so these are some combinational blocks that we've already seen.
Let's see some more.
Essentially you design combinational logic to build more complex systems and we actually think of
these combinational blocks as modules.
It's they we want to hide the unnecessary gate double details to emphasize the function of the
block.
For example, we say an adder and I want to think about only an adder, right?
Adder does addition.
I don't want to think about the underlying gates, but that adder actually compose is composed of the
underlying gates.
So we're going to build an adder or some other thing based on those underlying gates and then later
forget about it.
That's the beauty of abstraction, right?
You know exactly how an adder is built.
But once you know how an adder is built, you can forget about how it's built, at least for the
purpose of constructing something larger, something more complex.
OK, we're going to look at some blocks that are very useful for many, many, many things that we will
do.
They're also fun.
Decoder, multiplexer, full adder and programmable logic arrays.
Have you guys seen that before?
Any of these maybe?
OK, some of you, yes, many of you know that's good.
This is actually what we are going to cover.
Probably.
We're not going to finish all of this today, but let's see how what kind of things we can cover.
Decoder is very useful.
It's essentially an input pattern detector.
You have N inputs, and you have two to the N outputs and N inputs.
Only one input corresponding to a particular output is set to 1 and everything else becomes zero.
You can think of it that way.
Exactly 1 of the outputs is 1 and all of the rest are zeros, depending on the pattern in the inputs.
The output, or in other words the output that is logically 1, is the output that's corresponding to
the input pattern the logic circuit is expected to detect.
So let's take a look at 2:00 to 4:00 decoder.
This is the truth table.
You have two inputs and you have 4 outputs and if the input is 001 of the outputs and exactly one of
them is set to 1, everything else is set to 0.
If it's 01, this other output is set to 1.
Everything else is set to 0.
If it's 10, this output is set to 1 and everything else is set to 0.
If it's if the input is 11 Y 3 is set to 1 and everything else is set to 0.
Basically, you're really detecting what is your input pattern or you can think of this as an encoded
version.
And this is a decoded version, right?
And this is the abstraction level that we're going to construct the gate level representation of
this.
But this is the abstraction that we have two inputs A1A04 outputs because two inputs can take 4
combinations and depending on the combination, only one of the output is set and it's unique per
the input combination.
Now you know exactly how to construct this, right?
You can have a sum of products form for Y0Y1Y2Y3, right?
Correct.
Let's let's do it.
This is it basically.
So this is I think Y0.
Let's go back.
So Y0 is equal to a bar and D bar, right?
That's the sum of products form and that's what we have over here, A bar and B bar.
So Y0 is 1 if A&B are both 0, this is Y1 is 1 if a IS0B is 1 and you can do the rest.
Basically this is your decoder basically.
Makes sense, right?
And this is actually a nice decoder.
It's if you have input 10, you can figure out that this will be activated and everything else will
be 0.
OK, so we just built a decoder.
You can think of this as an exercise.
If someone gave you the truth table, you could build it easily based on the logic gates and the
truth table, right?
If someone gave you the functional specification without the truth table, you can construct the
truth table 1st and then take the sum of products form and build this, right?
Yes, there's a question.
Say it again.
If you use what gates OR gates, I mean, you could do it, Yeah.
I mean, in the end, you can convert all of these gates to other gates.
I'm sure there's a cheaper way.
I'm not sure if it's with the OR gates.
OK.
I think with the, you will have the same type of complexity with the OR gates because if you want to
convert, for example, the first one to OR gates, what you do is you you need to push out the
bubbles.
So it's going to be nor of A&B.
So it's going to be the same complexity with the OR gates, I think.
But there could be other tricks you can play at the transistor level, which I'm not going to get
into right now.
OK, very good.
It's good to think about optimizations.
OK, so the decoder, what is it useful for, right?
Why do we decode things?
Basically, it's useful for many things that we're going to see in the future.
For example, when we cover sequential logic, you will see that there's a memory address and we want
to figure out where to access which part of the memory.
Memory is A2 dimensional array, Which row am I going to access based on the input address?
So that's when decoder will be useful, right?
So essentially, it could be the address of a location in memory that the processor intends to read
from.
We're going to use a lot of decoders for that.
When we build memories, it could be an instruction when we talk about instructions.
So how does the software communicate that the processor needs to do an add or multiply or XOR?
We're going to encode that using a bit pattern.
XOR will have a bit pattern different from AND, which will be a different from different bit pattern
from multiply, and that's going to be our instruction set.
Every instruction will be encoded with a different bit pattern, and when the processor gets that bit
pattern to understand what kind of instruction to execute, it will need to decode that and activate
a particular part of the circuit like an adder so they can do ADD.
And that line coming out of the decoder will decide which part of the circuit to activate.
Hopefully this magic is becoming a little bit less magic right now, right?
But we're going to build up to that.
OK, Multiplexer.
That's another very basic component.
It's also called a selector.
It selects one of the north inputs.
To connect to connect it to the output based on the value of a control input called select.
And this control input is logged 2 to the north bits.
OK, let's take a look at the simplest multiplexer, 2 to 1 Max 2.
It's called the Max also.
So there are three inputs, 2 of them are data inputs D1D0 that you're selecting from, and one of
them is the select input.
So there are actually 3 inputs for a Max.
But data inputs are two select inputs.
Control input is 1 and Y is the output.
And this is the truth table.
So the truth table looks complicated, but it's not complicated if S IS0Y is equal to D0, right?
So you can see that if S IS0Y is the same as D0.
If S is 1, Y is the same as D1, right?
And this is what a multiplexer looks like.
This is how we denote it.
If S IS0Y is equal to D0.
If S is 1, Y is equal to D1, so there's a 0, there's a, there's a data input at the zero select
position and there's a data input at the one select position and it's depending on the select
value, the data input at that position gets passed to the output.
OK, but again, this is magic, meaning it's a high level module.
It can be implemented using logic gates that we have seen.
Let's do that.
And this is our product of sum of products form.
Let's yeah.
So basically this is OK, let's go through this quickly.
This is what we have essentially this is the select input.
And this is A, this is B.
If S IS0A needs to pass and if S is 1B passes, right?
That's what's implemented over here as you can see.
So let's take a look at this pictorially.
If S is 0, this input over here is 1.
So the output of this and gate is A.
If S is 0, this the output of this and gate is zero and a or 0 is A.
And you can do the same thing for B.
And this is 1 implementation of the multiplexer that we have seen.
Makes sense, right?
OK, you can implement it with NOR gates also, product of sums form also etcetera.
But I'm not going to do that.
OK.
The output C is always connected to either the input A or input B and output value depends on the
select line S and this is the representation.
This is another way of doing the truth table.
It's kind of a more condensed form of the truth table, right?
It's kind of abusing the truth table in a sense.
Because normally in a in a canonical truth table, you have inputs on the left and all of the input
combinations on the left and outputs on the right.
Here, implicitly you have two inputs A&B, right, and they don't appear on the left, right.
But this is a nice way of thinking about a multiplexer.
If the select line is 0, output is A.
If the select line is 1, output is B, right?
Sounds good.
Hopefully.
OK, your task, which I'm going to solve in the next slide is draw a schematic for a four to one
multiplexer.
Meaning you have 4 inputs, you select one of them.
You can do it gate level as a combination of basic and or not gates, or you can do it as a module
level as a combination of two input maxes, 2 to 1 maxes and both of them are here actually.
So your task became my task.
This is from your book also by the way.
Basically you can you can convince yourself that this is the two level logic that implements A4 to 1
multiplexer.
4 data inputs, 2 select inputs because there are four data inputs.
Log 2 to the four S 2 and if based on the value of S1 and S0 you select one and only one of them.
For example if S0 is 0 S 1 is 0D0Y is equal to D0.
If S0 is 1 S, 1 is 0, you select D1 over here, and this is the module level.
Basically, you can build a four to one multiplexer as a tree of two to one multiplexers.
So this is the two to one multiplexer.
This is the 2 to 1 multiplexer.
You select between D0 and D1 first.
You select between D2 and D3 first based on S0.
This is S0.
That's not a nice notation, but that's your, that's what your book did.
Still, it's S0 kind of implicitly.
The line is going underneath the module over there and based on the things that you selected, you
select one more based on the value of S1.
OK, this does the same thing as this, except this is implemented in a different way.
OK, OK.
So I'll do this aside because it's really important, especially for your labs where you will see
Fpgas like field programmable gate arrays and they will use look up tables and you can actually do
logic functions using multiplexers.
Also, multiplexer itself is a logic element, right?
It's a combination logic circuit, but you can build other logic functions using multiplexers.
And this is fun to think of by treating them as look up tables.
So let's take a look at this example from your books book.
So this is a 4 to 1 multiplexer expensive logic like we've seen for whatever reason, you may want to
implement an and logic function using this 4 to 1 multiplexer.
I know and is easier to build by itself.
But if all you have is a multiplexer, you can implement the and based on that.
How do you do that?
Well this is the.
This is the truth table of and right?
What you do is you think of the truth table as a look up table and you select the output value based
on the input values.
Since you have 4 possible combination of inputs and you have two select lines over here.
Select lines can select the outputs based on the and select lines can act as the inputs right?
So in this case, the 00, if a IS0B is 0, you get a 0 because those are tied to ground.
This is tied to a high voltage, which is power.
And only if A&B are 1, you get the one output at Y Makes sense, right?
So this is how Fpgas operate, and we're going to see that a little bit more because they use these
multiplexers.
They need to be programmable and multiplexers or look up tables are useful.
This is another example over here.
This is a better way of implementing it with a 2 to 1 Max if you have two to the one Max, right?
Again, this is the same function.
Y is equal to A&B.
You can collapse things.
This is actually how things are simplified.
So Y is equal to 0 if a is equal to 0 and Y is equal to B if a is equal to 1.
We're kind of playing tricks, right?
Boolean tricks.
And you set the A as the select line and B as the input to the one when the and the select line is 1
and otherwise you select the ground which is zero.
OK, this is another example over here.
This is an XOR function.
Again, you can do it on your own.
You can convince yourself that this multiplexer implements an XOR function.
Now this is becoming interesting right?
You can use the same end to 1 multiplexer to implement different functions.
So multiplexers are not that bad after all, and that's why Fpgas have been quite powerful.
And you're going to program those Fpgas to do some of these functions.
It's good to know how they operate.
This is another example.
If you have an 8 to 1 multiplexer, you can implement this particular function.
As you can see.
Again, I'll let you study this on your own.
It's from your book also, but it's the same concept.
You enumerate all of the midterms inputs and you tie them to what output values they're supposed to
take based on the look up tables, and you use the input values to the function as select lines.
That's it.
Not the most efficient way of implementing a function, but it is a way of implementing a function.
This programble, meaning you can connect those things to something else.
As you will see over here.
This is the free input.
Look up table.
This is the multiplexer.
What we have seen.
You'll go and see this in the FPGA in the lab lecture also next week sometime.
This is the select input.
So you can program this look up table and this three lot in FPGA term it's called 3 lot.
It could be used to implement any three input function, 3 bit input function.
And for example there is this example that you will see again next week, a function that outputs one
when there are at least 2 ones in a three bit input.
You can implement that as a look up table.
You can figure out which input combinations have at least 2 ones set their look up table entries to
1.
Everything else's look up table entries are zero, and based on the input that you get, you get the
correct output.
Instead of designing logic, you use a multiplexer to implement the function.
Multiplexer itself is logic.
So we're still designing logic, but we're not designing specialised logic for this function.
We're just programming a look up table.
So it's going to be more fun as you go into the labs and Fpgas.
OK, you can similarly use logic.
You do logic using decoders.
I will mention this and then we're going to finish and there will be an announcement from your
colleagues very quickly.
You may win, I don't know, $10,000.
OK, wow.
I would like to win that before we go on to full ladder.
So basically decoders can be combined with OR gates to build.
Functions also this is a 2 to 4 recorder.
What decoder does is decodes the minterms as you can see.
So if you want to do X nor of A&B, this is how you can connect.
So you basically connect the minterm AB and minterm AB bar to this or gate and that's what it is.
So this is a decoder and we're going to see more of this in the next lecture when we we'll start
with full adder.
OK, I'll see you next week, but there's a short announcement from your colleagues.
Hack is truly a universe of opportunities.
I learnt so much about teamwork, how everyone has some skills and how to bring it together for one
project.
I would recommend anyone to take up this chance and seize the moment.
The winner of Start Hack 2025 is Team.
We had one goal in mind and keep going and going and we used all these 36 hours to.
If are best and this case study.
So what you have seen here is one of the biggest hackathons in Europe.
It's going to be in March, using it for 10 years.
And we've got people coming from America, from Germany, Italy, and of course, Switzerland.
So we invite you to take part of this, to this international hackathon with many, many universities.
So yeah, we bring together over 600 hackers.
Everything is included.
So everything is free.
We have some problems with the PowerPoint, but I it's such a good opportunity to dive into a real
and concrete cases to go from theory to practice and not just to stay at uni and doing some yeah
theory you can apply now or just take a picture the application close really soon so like do it now
you can develop solutions for plenty of industries from finance to government to AI.
We've got case partners who yeah, who do finance.
You can code softwares to control drones.
That was one of the hack we had before.
So it's you've really got a good choice to do what you want and to make something that people will
actually use.
Thank you.